Guide to the Great White Fleet ephemera M1883
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Great White Fleet ephemera
circa 1901-1910
M1883
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
1.5 Linear feet
Postcards, lithographs, clippings, and other material related to the Great White Fleet and the United States Navy.
Scope and Contents
On December 16, 1907, the Great White Fleet of 16 battleships, 6 torpedo boats and 4 auxiliaries from the Atlantic fleet left Hampton Roads, Virginia for a round-the-world trip that would last over 2 years. President Teddy Roosevelt conceived of the idea of sending the fleet around the world as promotion for the United States in the wake of the Sino-Japanese war. Pictorial material including postcards, photographs, lithographs, magazine articles, a world map (map folder 3), flag (map folder 3), neptune certificate (map folder 2), sheet music (map folder 1), etc. The collection is based primarily on material from Mr. Edward Branning, electrician on the U.S.S. Rhode Island; other sources were later added.
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use.
Separated Materials note
The three oversize items in map folders were cataloged individually but retain the M1883 number.
Branning, Edward D.; United States. Navy.; United States--History, Naval--20th century
- 5 sheets from the Art Supplement to the Philadelphia Inquirer, dating June 19, April 24, July 2, June 19, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  5 sheets from the Art Supplement to the Philadelphia Inquirer, dating June 19, April 24, July 2, June 19, 1898. Colored photographic chromolithographs of the armored cruiser, New York, with inset portrait of Wm. T. Sampson; the USS battleship Kentucky; US protected cruiser San Francisco; US cruiser New Orleans; US armored cruiser Brooklyn, flagship.
- 24 Sub Post Card Co. views of the ships in the Great White Fleet (Box 1, Folder 2)
  24 Sub Post Card Co. black & white views of the ships in the Great White Fleet, published in Los Angeles. A letter written home covers the backs of 7 of them. This spectator of the fleet watched as it entered San Diego "sailing up from Mexico 16 abreast"... "Greatest parade I ever witnessed of 5000 sailors marching through the streets...".
- 4 real photo postcards of the USS Kearsarge, Arizona, cruiser Cincinnati & crew members. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 9 color printed postcards (Box 1, Folder 4)
  9 color printed postcards, with postmarks of various ships of the fleet including Under Pepper Trees (SS South Dakota); Contact Mines ready to land; Torpedo Tube & Torpedo on US torpedo boat; US marines with rapid fire gun; Entrance to Naval Academy, Annapolis (USS Franklin); US Marine Barracks Annapolis MD (USS Kansas); Culibra Cut (USS Oregon); Coconut Palms, Hawaii (USS Colorado); view Franklyn Park Boston (USS Washington).
- 24 color postcards published by Edward Mitchell of San Francisco (Box 1, Folder 5)
  24 color postcards published by Edward Mitchell of San Francisco of the ships of the fleet with details of their officer, length and batteries. Including USS Battleship "Connecticut", USS Battleship "Kearsarge", USS Battleship "Missouri"; USS Armored Cruiser "Pennsylvania"; USS armored Cruiser "California"; US Protected Cruiser "Charleston"; US Battleship "Minnesota" US Battleship "Georgia" (tipped in album); US armored cruiser "South Dakota"; US Battleship "Rhode Island"; US Battleship "Maine"; US Armored Cruiser "Washington"; US Armored Cruiser "Tennessee"; US Armored Cruiser "Charleston";US Battleship "Kentucky"; Crew of US Battleship "Rhode Island"; US Battleship "Virginia"; US Battleship "Missouri"; Battleship "Nebraska"; US Battleship "Maine"; US Battleship "Oregon"; US Battleship "Oregon" in dry dock; US Armored Cruiser "California"; US Battleship "New Jersey."
- 68 color photographs of ships (Box 1, Folders 6-19)
  50 tipped into an album, 18 loose.
- 4 portraits of "Bob" Evans (commander of the fleet), each with a different verse of a poem. (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Set of 9 Alan Fanjoy postcards (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Set of 9 greeting postcards in an Art Nouveau design by Alan Fanjoy Publish Publishers, Ocean Park, CA including USS Ohio, Maine, Yanklan, Glacier, Rhode Island, Illinois, Virginia, Missouri, New Jersey.
- Clippings re: postmarks of Great White Fleet (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Set of 6 Honey Boy cards (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Romantic postcards involving a sailor and his girl.
- 7 postcards sent to Miss Jean Pray of Long Island, 1908-1909 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Collection of 7 postcards sent to Miss Jean Pray of Long Island, 1908-09, showing views of ports visited including Jumbo Tree in Santa Cruz, California with fold-out of fleet; Landing San Diego April 11,1898; Punta Arenas; Honolulu 1908; Admiral Sperry, Yokohama Japan; Landing on Domain after parade Sydney (Australia); real photo view of deck off Manila ("bad storm, lost a shipmate").
- 2 California Cards, 1 folding, welcoming the fleet in 1908 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- 5 stereoscopic views of the Fleet (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Unused calendar, each month commemorating a ship of the Fleet, issued by the Holyoke Mutual Fire Insurance Co., 1908 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- 2 complementary ball invitations, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- 3 real photos, 1 of the Bennington sunk, by Bailey, and 2 on board the Wyoming, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Hat band of the USS Wyoming (Box 2, Folder 2)
- 3 color photo lithographs of ships including the Columbia, the Oregon's race of Cuba, and the Battleship Alabama (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Los Angeles City Public School certificate of donation to help replace the "Maine", destroyed in Havana in 1898 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Triple fold postcard, the Atlantic Fleet's departure by artist Nick F. Quirk, 1907-12 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- 12 offcuts of illustrated magazine articles about the Fleet (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Autograph of W.F. Ichley, Rear Admiral USA, 1899-12 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Life with the American Squadron: musical score by Harry V. Ingham (sheet music) (Map-folder 1)
- Neptune certificate given to Edward Branning to commemorate the crossing of the equator by the U.S.S. Rhode Island, 1908-01-06 (Map-folder 2)
- World map (Map-folder 3)